Guide to the Max Lerner Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Max Lerner papers
1927-1998
MS 322
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
102.79
(185 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, speeches, writings, and other papers, (including research and teaching materials, photographs, memorabilia, newspaper and periodical clippings, books, and radio and television tapes) of Max Lerner, an American educator, author, lecturer, historian, and political scientist. The papers focus on Lerner's public life and career with very little material on his personal or family life. The papers document Lerner's close association with Justice Felix Frankfurter and Harold J. Laski, his controversial writings on homosexuality, his work with the Democratic Party during Adlai Stevenson's presidential campaigns, his work on behalf of Jewish causes and Zionism, and his activities during the "red scare" of the 1950s.
Lerner, Max, 1902-1992
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Max Lerner, 1962, 1965, 1966, 1970, and 1981; gift of Richard Cummings, 1996; gift of Stephen Lerner, 1997 and 2004; gift of Robert Schmuhl, 2000, and 2010; purchase from Ardwright Chamberlain, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and six accessions: I. Correspondence, 1935-1969. II. Speeches and Writings, 1927, 1932-1969. III. Photographs, Press Clippings and Memorabilia, 1955-1969. IV. Books in the Max Lerner Papers.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Max Lerner in the Yale University Library are divided into four series and six additions: I. Correspondence; II. Speeches and Writing; and III. Photographs, Press Clippings, and Memorabilia. IV. Books in the Max Lerner Papers.
Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, has been divided into two sections. The first section contains Lerner's letters to and from important political, literary, and academic figures, and the publishers of his books. The collections begins in 1935 and continues until 1969. Harold J. Laski (approximately 120 letters) and Felix Frankfurter (approximately 350 letters) are probably the most important correspondents. Other major correspondents are Hugo L. Black (47 letters), Howard K. Beale (16 letters), Chester Bowles (21 letters), James M. Burns (21 letters), Hiram Haydn (75 letters), Bruce Bliven (100 letters), Eleanor Roosevelt (10 letters), Adlai Stevenson (8 letters), Arthur Schlesinger, Jr. (50 letters), and James Wechsler (35 letters). The letters deal entirely with Lerner's public life and career; no family or personal correspondence is in this collection.
The second section of correspondence contains letters from less prominent persons and from the general public. It is arranged in chronological order and runs from 1935 until 1969. Of particular interest are the letters from readers in response to Lerner's columns in the New York Post, especially in the early 1950s. Lerner wrote several columns on the activities of Senator Joseph R. McCarthy and a lengthy series on the Kinsey Reports and related subjects. The series produced the greatest reader response of any of Lerner's columns.
Series II, SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, the largest series, has been divided into four sections. The first contains Lerner's newspaper columns. A few are from the New York Star, but the columns appearing in the New York Post from 1949 until 1969 are almost complete, and these columns provide a useful guide to the evolution of Lerner's thought over the twenty year period. Background notes and rough drafts are included with many of the columns.
The second section of this series contains some of Lerner's printed magazine articles and the background notes for them. This collection is far from complete, and the notes are in an extremely dilapidated state. Many of Lerner's articles, however, appeared in The New Republic in the 1940s and early 1950s; so interested persons should consult the indices of the magazine for those years.
The third section contains some of Lerner's speeches and the background notes for others. Again the notes are in extremely poor condition. In the 1940s and early 1950s when the widespread use of tape recorders madetranscriptionmuch easer, many of Lerner's public addresses were transcribed and printed. This section also contains some lecture notes for the courses that Lerner taught at Sarah Lawrence College in the 1930s.
The fourth section contains the notes, drafts, and proofs of Lerner's published books. Included in this section are the course outlines and syllabi from Brandeis University which formed the basis for America as a Civilization. Also in this section are the notes, drafts, and fragments of the books which Lerner did not complete or publish.
Series III, PHOTOGRAPHS, PRESS CLIPPINGS, AND MEMORABLILA, contains photographs, mostly unidentified, press clippings, book reviews, printed programs, and other memorabilia. These items have not been arranged in any particular order. The last box contains 47 tape recordings of radio and television programs in which Lerner participated in the 1950s and 1960s. (Transferred to Historical Sound Recordings)
Series IV, BOOKS IN THE MAX LERNER PAPERS, contains books authored or edited by Max Lerner.
Biographical / Historical
Max Lerner was born in Minsk, Russia, in 1902 and came to the United States in 1907. His family lived first in New York City and then in New Haven, Connecticut, where he attended high school. Lerner received his B.A. degree from Yale University in 1923 and attended Yale Law School for one year. He received his M.A. degree from Washington University in 1925 and his Ph.D. from the Robert Brookings Graduate School of Economics and Government in 1927. He worked as assistant editor of the Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences and became managing editor. From 1932 until 1935 he taught political science at Sarah Lawrence College; he also taught at the Wellesley Summer Institute and the Harvard Summer School. From 1936 until 1938 he was editor of The Nation. In 1938 Lerner became professor of political science at Williams College, remaining there until 1943.
Throughout his career Lerner has been an active writer, commentator, and lecturer. From 1943 until 1948 he was editorial director of the newspaper PM and in 1948 and 1949 he was a columnist for its successor the New York Star. In 1949 Lerner became a regular columnist for the New York Post; his column appeared three times weekly for more than twenty years. Active in the founding of Brandeis University, Lerner became professor of American Civilization there in 1949 and remained there until his retirement. His well-known book, America as a Civilization, in large part grew out of his Brandeis course.
Lerner wrote many magazine articles and in the 1950s and 1960s spoke frequently before educational associations, college and university groups, religious and civic organizations, and on television and radio programs. He is the author of It is Later Than You Think (1938 rev. ed 1943), Ideas are Weapons (1939), Ideas for the Ice Age (1941), The Mind and Faith of Justice Holmes (1943), Public Journal (1945), The Portable Veblen (1948), Actions and Passions (1949), America as a Civilization (1957), The Unfinished Country (1959), The Essential Works of John Stuart Mill (1961), The Age of Overkill (1962), Education and a Radical Humanism (1962), and Tocqueville and American Civilization(1969).
Lerner married Anita Marburg in 1928, and they had three daughters: Constance, Pamela (dec.), and Joanna. They were divorced in 1940, and in 1941 he married Edna Albers; they had three sons: Michael, Stephen, and Adam. Max Lerner died mid 1992.
New York post; New York star; PM (New York, N.Y.); Gay liberation movement -- United States; Historiography; Homosexuality -- United States; Jews, American; Journalism; Philosophy; Race relations -- United States; Zionism; Israel; New York (N.Y.) -- Newspapers; United States -- History -- 20th Century; United States -- Politics and government; Authors; Educators; Political scientists; Abram, Morris B.; Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971; Albee, Edward, 1928-2016; Allen, Robert S. (Robert Sharon), 1900-1981; Alsop, Joseph, 1910-1989; Alsop, Stewart, 1914-1974; Arendt, Hannah, 1906-1975; Baldwin, Roger N. (Roger Nash), 1884-1981; Ball, George W., 1909-; Barnard, Harry, 1906-1982; Baxter, James Phinney, 1831-1921; Beale, Howard K. (Howard Kennedy), 1899-1959; Beard, Charles A. (Charles Austin), 1874-1948; Becker, Carl L. (Carl Lotus), 1873-1945; Bell, Daniel, 1919-2011; Benét, William Rose, 1886-1950; Benton, Thomas Hart, 1889-1975; Biddle, Francis, 1886-1968; Black, Hugo LaFayette, 1886-1971; Bliven, Bruce, 1889-1977; Block, Herbert, 1909-2001; Bond, Horace Mann, 1904-1972; Boorstin, Daniel J. (Daniel Joseph), 1914-2004; Borkenau, Franz, 1900-1957; Bowles, Chester, 1901-1986; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963; Brownell, Doris; Buckley, William F., Jr., 1925-2008; Bundy, McGeorge, 1919-1996; Burns, James MacGregor, 1918-2014; Burton, Harold H. (Harold Hitz), 1888-1964; Camus, Albert, 1913-1960; Carr, Edward Hallett, 1892-1982; Casals, Pablo, 1876-1973; Catton, Bruce, 1899-1978; Chagall, Marc, 1887-1985; Chaplin, Charlie, 1889-1977; Chase, Richard, 1904-1988; Chase, Stuart, 1888-1985; Church, Frank; Clark, Tom C. (Tom Campbell), 1899-1977; Clifford, Clark M., 1906-1998; Cohn, Alfred E. (Alfred Einstein), 1879-1957; Commager, Henry Steele, 1902-1998; Cooke, Alistair, 1908-2004; Cooke, Morris Llewellyn, 1872-1960; Cooper, John Sherman, 1901-1991; Cousins, Norman, 1912-1990; Coward, Noel, 1899-1973; De Voto, Bernard, 1897-1955; Deutsch, Karl W. (Karl Wolfgang), 1912-1992; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980; Durant, Will, 1885-1981; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969; Ellison, Ralph, 1914-1994; Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1904-1979; Forrestal, James, 1892-1949; Fortas, Abe, 1910-1982; Frank, Jerome, 1889-1957; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965; Freeman, Orville L., 1918-2003; Fromm, Erich, 1900-1980; Fuchs, Lawrence H., 1927-2013; Fulbright, J. William (James William), 1905-1995; Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1908-2006; Gandhi, Indira, 1917-1984; Gardner, John W. (John William), 1912-2002; Garrison, Lloyd K. (Lloyd Kirkham), 1897-1991; Geismar, Maxwell, 1909-1979; Ginzburg, Ralph, 1929-2006; Goldberg, Arthur J., 1908-; Goldwater, Barry M. (Barry Morris), 1909-1998; Graham, Katharine, 1917-2001; Greene, Graham, 1904-1991; Griffin, Robert P. (Robert Paul), 1923-2015; Gunther, John, 1901-1970; Hackett, Francis, 1883-1962; Hand, Learned, 1872-1961; Handlin, Oscar, 1915-2011; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986; Haydn, Hiram Collins, 1907-1973; Hefner, Hugh M. (Hugh Marston), 1926-2017; Helms, Richard, 1913-2002; Hobson, Laura Z. (Laura Zametkin), 1900-1986; Hofstadter, Richard, 1916-1970; Horney, Karen, 1885-1952; Hughes, Emmet John, 1920-; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952; Ingersoll, Ralph, 1900-1985; Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986; Johnson, Alvin Saunders, 1874-1971; Kazan, Elia, 1909-2003; Kennan, George F. (George Frost), 1904-2005; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963; Kinsey, Alfred C. (Alfred Charles), 1894-1956; Kirchwey, Freda; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Lamont, Corliss, 1902-1995; Landers, Ann; Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-1987; Lange, Oskar, 1904-1965; Laski, Harold J. (Harold Joseph), 1893-1950; Lasswell, Herbert; Lerner, Alan Jay, 1918-1986; Lerner, Max, 1902-1992; Levin, Meyer, 1905-1981; Levy, Leonard W. (Leonard Williams), 1923-2006; Lewis, John L. (John Llewellyn), 1880-1969; Lindner, Robert Mitchell, 1914-1956; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet), 1921-2000; Lynd, Helen Merrell, 1896-1982; Lynd, Robert Staughton, 1892-1970; Lynd, Staughton; Macdonald, Dwight, 1906-1982; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982; Mailer, Norman, 1923-2007; Malle, Louis, 1932-1995; Malraux, André, 1901-1976; Manchester, William, 1922-2004; Mankiewicz, Frank, 1924-2014; Mansfield, Mike, 1903-2001; Marcuse, Herbert, 1898-1979; Maritain, Jacques, 1882-1973; Marshall, Thurgood, 1908-1993; McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-2005; McGovern, George S. (George Stanley), 1922-2012; McWilliams, Carey, 1905-1980; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978; Meiklejohn, Alexander, 1872-1964; Meir, Golda, 1898-1978; Mendès France, Pierre, 1907-1982; Menninger, Karl A. (Karl Augustus), 1893-1990; Michener, James A. (James Albert), 1907-1997; Miller, Henry, 1891-1980; Mills, C. Wright (Charles Wright), 1916-1962; Mondale, Walter F., 1928-; Monnet, Jean, 1888-1979; Montagu, Ashley, 1905-1999; Morgenthau, Hans J. (Hans Joachim), 1904-1980; Morison, Samuel Eliot, 1887-1976; Morse, Wayne L. (Wayne Lyman), 1900-1974; Moynihan, Daniel P. (Daniel Patrick), 1927-2003; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990; Muskie, Edmund S., 1914-1996; Nettels, Curtis P. (Curtis Putnam); Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Nizer, Louis, 1902-1994; Padover, Saul Kussiel, 1905-1981; Perkins, Frances, 1880-1965; Philbrick, Herbert A. (Herbert Arthur), 1915-1993; Reston, James, 1909-1995; Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970; Riesman, David, 1909-2002; Roche, John P. (John Pearson), 1923-1994; Rockefeller, John D., III (John Davison), 1906-1978; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962; Roosevelt, Elliott, 1910-1990; Rossiter, Clinton, 1917-1970; Rostow, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1913-2002; Rusk, Dean, 1909-1994; Sachar, Abram Leon, 1899-1993; Salinger, Pierre, 1925-2004; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967; Sartre, Jean-Paul, 1905-1980; Schiff, Dorothy, 1903-1989; Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007; Schuman, Frederick L. (Frederick Lewis), 1904-1981; Seldes, George, 1890-1995; Shriver, Sargent, 1915-2011; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968; Smedley, Agnes, 1892-1950; Spanel, A. N. (Abram Nathaniel), 1901-1985; Sparkman, John, 1899-1985; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965; Straight, Beatrice, 1914-2001; Straight, Michael Whitney, 1916-2004; Swope, Herbert Bayard, 1882-1958; Taylor, Elizabeth, 1912-1975; Thant, U, 1909-1974; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Thompson, Dorothy, 1893-1961; Toynbee, Arnold, 1889-1975; Trilling, Lionel, 1905-1975; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Tuchman, Barbara W. (Barbara Wertheim), 1912-1989; Valenti, Jack, 1921-2007; Wagner, Robert F. (Robert Ferdinand), 1910-1991; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965; Warren, Earl, 1891-1974; Wechsler, James A. (James Arthur), 1915-1983; Williams, Tennessee, 1911-1983; Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944; Wilson, Edmund, 1895-1972; Winchell, Walter, 1897-1972; Yorty, Sam, 1909-1998; Zinn, Howard, 1922-2010; United States. Central Intelligence Agency; Brandeis University; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997); Simon and Schuster, Inc
- Correspondence, 1935-1969; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is divided into two sections. The first is arranged alphabetically by name of the writer and contains letters form important political, literary, and academic figures. The second section is arranged chronologically and contains letters from less prominent persons and from the general public. Copies of letters written by Max Lerner are filed under the name of the person to whom they were addressed.
  - Selected Correspondence
    - Acheson, Dean, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Action Committee
      General
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 443
    - Abram, Morris, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Agriculture, Department of
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 139
    - Albee, Edward, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Allen, Frederic L., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Allen, Robert S., 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Alsop, Joseph Wright, 1946-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Alsop, Stewart J. O., 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - American Broadcasting Company, 1946, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - American Civil Liberties Union, 1943-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      See also: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 15
    - American Jewish Congress
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 320
    - American Scholar
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 178 - 182
    - America's Town Meeting of the Air
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 424 - 427
    - Ardrey, Robert, 1948-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Arendt, Hannah, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Arnold, Thurman, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Arvey, Jacob, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Ascoli, Max, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Baldwin, Roger, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Ball, George, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Barnard, Harry, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 17 - 18)
    - Barzan, Jacques, 1956, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Baxter, James P. III, 1938, 1943, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Beach, Keyes, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Beale, Howard K., 1946-1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Beard, Charles, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Beaverbrook, Rt. Hon. Lord, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Becker, Carl, 1935-1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Bell, Daniel, 1952-1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Benton, Thomas Hart, 1948, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Benton, William, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Berkeley, California, mayor of
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 203
    - Berlin, Isaiah, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Biddle, Francis, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Black, Hugo L., 1938-1969 (Box 1, Folder 31 - 34)
    - Bliven, Bruce, 1941-1955 (Box 1, Folder 35 - 40)
    - Block, Herbert (Herblock), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Blum, John M., 1955 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Boorstin, Daniel J., 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Boudin, Louis B., 1943 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Bowen, Catherine Drinker, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Bowker, Albert H., 1959, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Bowles, Chester, 1945-1969 (Box 1, Folder 47 - 48)
    - Bradley, Thomas, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Brandeis University
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 2
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 141
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 234 - 235
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 351
    - Brogan, Sir Dennis W., 1960 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Brookings Institution
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 57
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 159
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 401
    - Brownell, Doris (Mrs. Herbert), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Buchanan, Patrick J., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Buckley, William F., Jr., 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Bundy, Mc George, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Burns, James M., 1943-1966 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Burton, Harold H., 1949 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Calkins, Robert D., 1959, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Camus, Albert, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Canfield, Cass, 1967, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Cantril, Hadley, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Caradon, Rt. Hon. the Lord, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Carlson, John Roy, 1946-1947, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Casals, Pablo, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Catlin, George E. C., 1959, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Catton, Bruce, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 364
    - Central Intelligence Agency
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 184
    - Cerf, Bennett A., 1946, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Chagall, Marc, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Chaplin, Charles, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Christian, George, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Church, Frank, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Clark, Tom C., 1949 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Clifford, Clark, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Cohn, Alfred E., 1946, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Columbia Broadcasting System (C. B. S.), 1943-1949, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 75 - 78)
    - Commager, Henry S., 1955-1963 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Commins, Saxe, 1945-1953 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Cooke, Allister, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Cooke, Morris L., 1946, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Cooper, John Sherman, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Cousins, Norman, 1941-1950 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Coward, Noel, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Craven, Avery, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Cushman, Robert E., 1943-1949 (Box 2, Folder 87)
    - Dahl, Robert A., 1963 (Box 2, Folder 88)
    - Daniel, Clifton, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Day, Lincoln H., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Defense, Department of
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 73
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 111
      See: Series III. Photographs, Press Clippings, and Memorabilia 1955-1969 Folder 69
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 407
    - Democratic National Committee
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 169
    - DeSantillana, George, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 91)
    - DeVoto, Bernard, 1946, 1948, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 92)
    - Dilliard, Irving, 1950-1958 (Box 2, Folder 93)
    - Doar, John, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 94)
    - Donald, David, 1955, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 95)
    - Douglas, Paul H., 1948, 1951, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Douglas, William O., 1939, 1946, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Durant, Will, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Einstein, Albert, 1945-1949 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1952 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Elliot, W. Y., 1946-1950 (Box 2, Folder 101)
    - Ellison, Ralph, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Ekburg, Anita, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 103)
    - Evett, Robert, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Everett, John R., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Fainsod, Merle, 1944, 1949, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Fairchild, Henry Pratt, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Falk, Stanley, 1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 108)
    - Farrell, James, 1944, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Field, Marshall, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Ford Foundation
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 54
    - Foreign Service Institute
      See: Series I. Correspondence, 1935-1969 Folder 204
    - Forrestal, James, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Fortas, Abe, 1946, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - Frank, Jerome N., 1938, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - Frank, Waldo, 1944-1946 (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - Frankol, Roger, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 115)
    - Frankel, Charles, 1965, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 116)
    - Frankfurter, Felix, 1936-1957, undated (Box 3, Folder 117 - 137)
    - Freeman, John, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 138)
    - Freeman, Orville, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 139)
    - Fromm, Erich, 1954-1956 (Box 3, Folder 140)
    - Fuchs, Lawrence H., 1954-1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 141)
    - Fulbright, J. William, 1955, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 142)
    - Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1955-1956, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 143)
    - Gandhi, Indira, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 144)
    - Gardner, John W., 1968 (Box 3, Folder 145)
    - Garrison, Lloyd, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 146)
    - Gauss, Christian, 1945, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 147)
    - Gaylin, Willard, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 148)
    - Geismar, Maxwell, 1949-1957 (Box 3, Folder 149)
    - Gilbert, Felix, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 150)
    - Ginzburg, Ralph, 1958, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 151)
    - Glazer, Nathan, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 152)
    - Goldberg, Arthur, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 153)
    - Golden, Harry, 1965, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 154)
    - Goldman, Eric P., 1955 (Box 3, Folder 155)
    - Goldwater, Barry, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 156)
    - Goldwyn, Samuel, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 157)
    - Goodman, Paul, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 158)
    - Gordon, Kermit, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 159)
    - Graham, Frank, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 160)
    - Graham, Katharine Meyer, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 161)